In the Great Kyoho Famine in 1732, many died of starvation on Hitogashima.
1732年，享保大饑荒期間 日都島上接連出現餓殍
Just as the island was dying off, a whale washed up on Omotohama Beach.
就在島民生死存亡之際 一頭巨鯨漂流到了萬年青沙灘上
Overjoyed with this gift from God, the islanders gathered to devour it.
島民們認為這頭巨鯨是神的恩賜 十分高興，聚集在一起準備吃掉它
As a fisherman's daughter came, the whale's body suddenly flashed.
某個漁民的女兒靠近巨鯨時 巨鯨的身體發出了炫目的光
In a brink of an eye, it took the form of that girl.
在頃刻間，變成了那個小女孩的模樣
Then it consumed the girl.
並且吃掉了那個小女孩
Fearing a curse, people worshipped it as the living goddess Hiruko.
害怕遭天譴的島民將小女孩當作 蛭子大人的現人神，供奉了起來
This is the Hiruko's Lore, a Hitogashima legend.
這就是在日都島上流傳的蛭子傳承
MEETING
（第18集　面對面）
Do you sense any shadows?
有影子的氣息嗎？
No.
沒有
Ms. Nagumo was right. Karikiri is not a shadow.
看來南雲老師說得沒錯 雁切先生果然不是影子
Okay, but don't let your guard down.
是嗎？不過也不能掉以輕心
Got it.
嗯
Well, well. It's been so hot recently.
天啊，每天都好熱
Yes.
是啊
Is Tokyo hotter than Wakayama?
東京怎麼樣？比和歌山還要熱嗎？
No, it's not much different.
沒有，也差不多
Here, have some cold barley tea.
喝杯凍麥茶吧
Thank you. Didn't you come to Tokyo last year?
謝謝，不過雁切先生去年 不是去過東京嗎？
Huh?
甚麼？
Yesterday you told me that you went to a game event in Tokyo.
昨天不是說過嗎？去了東京的遊戲展
Ah! That's right. It was near the ocean, in Makuhari.
對，在離海很近的那個地方 是幕張，對吧？
Makuhari is in Chiba, but Tokyo really was hot!
幕張雖然是在千葉縣，是啊 東京真的好熱啊
There were so many people, too.
而且人山人海
You like games, don't you? What type do you play?
您真喜歡玩遊戲 一般都玩甚麼類型呢？
I used to love RPGs,
以前玩的都是RPG 現在喜歡PC的FPS類和模擬類的
Are you going again this year?
今年也會去嗎？
No, I probably won't make it this year.
不，今年應該去不了了
I was really looking forward to the FF7 Remake.
真想玩玩FF7的重製版啊 不知道甚麼時候才出
Is it good? I hear a lot about it.
FF7好玩嗎？經常聽人提起
What? You've never played it before?
甚麼？慎平你沒玩過第7代嗎？
I wasn't born yet when it first came out.
因為是我出生之前出的遊戲啊
Its worldview is unique, maybe because it came out at the end of the century.
我喜歡裡面的世界觀 可能因為上市時間是世紀末吧
Both its art and music have a mood of decadence.
藝術和音樂都給人一種頹廢感
It makes you think about the end of life.
令人思考人生結束的方式
Life? Games to you are like novels for me.
人生嗎？遊戲於雁切先生來說 就像小說之於我
Do you know the novel Swamp Man by Ryunosuke Nagumo?
您知道南雲龍之介的 《沼男》這本小說嗎？
I love it so much that it feels like it was written about my life.
我很喜歡，最近總覺得這本小說 寫的就是我的事情，是關於我的故事
I'm not familiar with that novel, but I know the Swamp Man theory.
我沒聽過《沼男》這本小說 不過我倒是知道思考實驗的「沼男」
Is it about that?
是類似的內容嗎？
Yes, a protagonist's copy appears and lives in his place.
是，講述某一天主角的複製人出現 並取代了主角的故事
No one at home or school notices that he is a copy.
家裡和學校都沒人發現他是複製人
It perfectly copies all memories, personality, and DNA of the original.
複製人完美複製了主角的記憶 人格和DNA
If that's the case, do you think that it is the same person as the orginal?
您覺得在這種情況之下，可以說 複製人和他本人就是同一個人嗎？
I would think it's the same person.
我覺得應該就是同一個人吧
Human cells are replaced each day, because of our metabolism.
人的細胞由於新陳代謝 每天都在更新
Our cells continuously divide and copy themselves.
重複著細胞分裂，也就是複製
Whether it was done in a flash or slowly won't make difference.
這只是瞬間發生 與緩慢發生的差別而已
So you believe a copy is the same as the original.
也就是說複製品和原型是一樣的
Yes, I do.
我是這麼認為的
Is this always on your mind? It was the shadow sickness yesterday.
你都在想這些事情嗎？ 昨天也來問我關於影子病的事情
I also looked into the Hiruko's Lore.
我還調查了蛭子傳承
I was going to ask you, then Hizuru told me the details.
本來還想來問問雁切先生 但日鶴小姐很詳細地告訴了我
Around 300 years ago in the Edo period, a god Hiruko drifted to this island.
在大概300年前的江戶時代 有個神漂流到這島上，就是蛭子大人
In the far past, it arrived from outside this realm, let's say, space.
那是在遠古時期，從這世界以外來的 先假設是宇宙吧
It was an organism that lived in outer space.
它是一種漂浮在宇宙中的生命體
It copied nearby objects, transformed, and consumed the copied data,
它會複製並變身為近處的物體 以複製的情報為營養
but it had a limited choice of objects to transform into in space.
但宇宙空間內可變身的物體有限
It probably came down to Earth in the form of a meteorite.
所以它恐怕是以隕石的形態 來到地球上的
It fell into the ocean, and copied many things.
它應該掉入了大海 並複製了各種生物
Up to this point is Hizuru's theory.
到這裡為止只是日鶴小姐的想像
However, the rest of the story is in the written records of Hiruko's Lore.
但接下來的內容就與文獻中的 蛭子傳承聯繫起來了
300 years ago, it transformed into a whale,
300年前，它變身成了鯨魚
and for some reason, it washed up on this island.
之後由於某些原因 它漂流到這座島上
It copied a fisherman's daughter who came to see the whale.
複製了前來看鯨魚的那群人之中 某個漁民的女兒
That was the start of the shadow sickness.
那就是影子病的開端
That's what they say in Hiruko's Lore. Are you saying that it's a true story?
蛭子傳承的確是這樣寫的 不過你不會認為這故事是真事吧？
Yes. Shadows exist.
是的，影子是真實存在的
Like they killed Ushio and my parents,
而且影子殺了潮，殺了我的父母
they will kill everyone who come to these grounds tomorrow.
明天還會殺掉 聚集在這神社院內的所有人
I know you're upset about Ushio's death. You need some rest.
我知道小潮的死對你打擊肯定很大 你還是好好休息一下
I know everything.
我已經全都弄清楚了
Karikiri, you knew that this is a true story.
雁切先生，你知道我說的都是事實
After all, you've watched it all unfold.
因為你從頭到尾都在看著這一切發生
What is it?
那是甚麼？
A whale?
是鯨魚
I didn't notice at first, but Dr. Hishigata pointed you out.
一開始我沒有發現
The man on your right is Dr. Hishigata's grandfather.
站在右側的男性 似乎是菱形醫生的爺爺
Why are you in a photograph that is 70 years old?
70年前的老照片，為甚麼會拍到您？
Masahito Karikiri, or Shidehiko Hishigata?
雁切真砂人先生，不，菱形紙垂彥
You are Shide.
你就是四手
Heine!
波稻
Come back here, Heine!
快回來，波稻，波…
Heine? Come here.
波稻，快過來
Ah, Mr. Shide.
紙垂大人
Shinpei...
慎平…
Move, and I'll kill you.
不許動，動就殺了你
What has Dr. Hishigata told you?
菱形醫生說了甚麼？
I'm asking questions here. Look at the other photograph.
我不會回答你的問題，提問的是我 再看另一張照片
That one is from 40 years ago. Dr. Hishigata's father took it.
時代變遷，這張40年前的照片 應該是菱形醫生的父親所拍的
You are not a shadow, but not human either.
你不是影子，但你也不是普通的人類
Swamp Man...
沼男…
Hiruko? Why would it be here?
蛭子大人？為甚麼會在這裡？
I don't know. Just a guess.
不清楚，這只是我的推測
If so, Hishigata Clinic and Hito Shrine must be connected somehow.
但如果這就是蛭子大人的話 即是菱形醫院和日都神社有關聯嗎？
The identity of Four-arm could be Masahito Karikiri.
四隻手臂的真正身分 也許是雁切真砂人
Huh? The Karikiri boy?
甚麼？你說雁切的兒子？
Aren't you thinking the same thing?
你們也是這麼認為的吧？
Yes.
是
If Hiruko is the mother of shadows, the shrine worshipping her is suspicious.
波稻…蛭子大人如果是影子的母親 那供奉她的日都神社一定很可疑
Karikiri is the priest there.
而且雁切先生還是神社的宮司
Yeah, but isn't Karikiri a human?
可是雁切是人類吧
Why would Four-arm hide its face? If it were a shadow, it should transform.
四隻手臂為甚麼要遮住臉？ 如果他是影子，只要變成別人就行了
What if it is actually a human who is incapable of copying?
但假設他是人類，沒有複製能力呢？
I've never seen it scan anything, but it did print.
沒看過那傢伙掃描，但他列印過
If Four-arm is a human
那些黑色的泥是構成影子的物質
who wears the sludge of shadows as an armor...
而四隻手臂就是將那種泥 像鎧甲一樣穿在身上的人類呢？
It wants to hide its face because we would recognize him.
把臉遮住是害怕被人看到 也就是說，他是我們認識的人
SIXTH LOOP JULY 22 AFTER CANCELING ENTRY TO KOBA MART
（第六輪，7月22日 中止衝入小早超市的計劃後）
How could it do that to Ryunosuke. Four-arm must be Masahito Karikiri.
那傢伙竟然把龍之介… 四隻手臂果然就是雁切真砂人
I am certain after facing it in your memories.
剛才在你的記憶中 與他面對面後，我確信了
How could you tell?
你怎麼知道的？
I never liked that priest.
我從小就討厭那個宮司 四隻手臂也同樣讓我生理上無法接受
What do you mean?
你在說甚麼？
He can hide his face, but not what's inside.
鎧甲可以遮住臉，卻遮不住個性
The fact that Nezu's shots didn't work can be explained if it's human.
而且根津的縫影對他無效 更提高了他是人類的可能性
However, Karikiri was at the funeral during that time.
可是雁切先生那個時候 應該還在葬禮會場
Maybe he sent his shadow to the funeral.
葬禮也許是交給影子去主持了
If there really is a human inside, we can assassinate him.
如果那裡面真是個人類 那我們就能暗殺他了
If he is human, killing him is easy.
如果他是個普通人 要殺他根本就很簡單
I'll casually visit the shrine, and shoot him while we chat.
裝作不知情的樣子去神社找他 閒聊過程中，趁其不備給他一槍
That's murder!
那可是殺人啊
We need more evidence.
必須有確鑿的證據才行
We might be able to persuade him too.
而且如果他是人類的話 把他逼到絕境或許還能與他談談
Shide burned his left hand. It shall help us find his identity.
四手的左手被燒傷了 這會成為判斷他真實身分的標記
Look at this.
看看這張照片
Shide is Heine's guardian, and the first child Heine bore.
那傢伙是波稻的守護者 也是她生下的第一個孩子
Its original is Shidehiko Hishigata, founder of the Hishigata Clinic.
原型的名字是菱形紙垂彥 是菱形醫院的創始人，第一任院長
What is this photograph?
這張照片是怎麼回事？
The Hishigata family was in charge of religious ceremonies on the island,
菱形家自古就擔任這座島的祭祀之職
until Shidehiko's father began playing doctor in the Edo period.
到了江戶時代 紙垂彥的父親開始行醫
Did you say Hishigata? The Karikiris have the shrine.
等等，甚麼菱形… 神社不是雁切家的嗎？
Karikiris and Hishigatas are related. They branched off from Hishigatas.
菱形和雁切本來就是同一家 雁切是從菱形家分出去的家系
Are you familiar with Hiruko's Lore?
你們都知道蛭子傳承吧？
The day Hiruko drifted here, Hiruko became Heine, and then a god.
蛭子漂流而來的那一天 蛭子化身為波稻
That's right.
是的
In time, Shidehiko had a child with this god.
不久後紙垂彥與神結合，誕下子嗣
The child wasn't born from a scanned shadow.
他不是通過掃描 以影子的形態從平面當中分娩出來的
He got Heine's body pregnant, and she gave birth to a child.
而是讓波稻的肉體懷孕所生出來的
He called himself a god's husband, and took Heine's surname, Karikiri.
之後他便自稱「神之夫」 並以波稻的姓氏雁切自居
Shidehiko had a brother.
而且紙垂彥還有個哥哥
After Heine gave birth, the Hishigata family split,
波稻生產後，菱形家就分家了
and Karikiris became priests while Hishigatas were doctors.
之後由雁切家祭神 而菱形家成為醫生世家
So Shide and we are blood-related?
也就是說四手和我們 是有血緣關係的遠親？
I can't believe it.
怎麼會…
What happened to the child?
那個生下來的孩子後來怎麼樣了？
When the child grew older, it was a splitting image of Shidehiko.
隨著那孩子漸漸成長 他和紙垂彥長得越來越像同一個人
That must be the nature of a shadow.
這應該就是影子的性質吧
A child from Heine's pregnancy is the father's clone.
波稻懷孕所生下的孩子 就是父親的複製體
Shidehiko notices this, and kindles a certain desire.
接下來才是重點 看到這一切的紙垂彥萌生了某種欲望
It can't be.
該不會…
He made Heine copy and implant his personality and memory in the clone.
那傢伙讓波稻複製了 自己的人格和記憶，移植到複製體上
In this way, he was reborn.
藉此回復青春
Such a sick bastard. No wonder I hated him.
令人作嘔，怪不得我這麼厭惡他
My father helped deliver the baby, and took that photo.
負責接生的是我的父親 而那張照片也是父親拍下來的
His current body was born that day. Shide repeated this technique.
那傢伙現在的肉體 就是當時生下來的那個
He made Heine give birth to his new body over and over,
不斷讓生下自己的波稻再生下自己
and that's how he has lived for 300 years now.
他就這樣從300年前存活至今
You're a hybrid of human and shadow.
人與影子的雜交體
Well, well, Shinpei. You don't play fair. You loop.
不得了，慎平，你太狡猾了 畢竟能輪迴啊
You can't possibly know so much in just one day.
剛回老家一天就查到這麼多了
Take a seat and have some tea. It's not poisoned.
坐下來喝杯茶怎麼樣？我可沒下毒
So you admit it.
即是你承認了吧？
I was 40 years old back then.
當時，我40歲的時候
It was the summer of 1732, the year of the Great Kyoho Famine.
那是1732年的夏天
Do you know about it? It's in the textbooks.
你知道那段歷史嗎？ 日本史的教科書上有教
We had a terrible harvest year. Fishermen died, so we had no fish either.
當時嚴重歉收
But then, Heine showed up.
但那時波稻出現了
Islanders believed that god was in items that drifted ashore,
這座島一直以來都信奉 從海上漂來之物寄宿著神明
so they believed Heine was a god.
波稻簡直就是神明降臨
In exchange for eating the people, Heine blessed the fishing.
而島民將人類供奉給她食用 換來島上的漁業豐收
No,
那個傳承這一段說得不對
because shadows can easily catch fish and save people from starving.
影子就算不是漁民也能捕魚 這才拯救了那些饑餓的人
Hitogashima still exists, thanks to me.
日都島能有今天，都是多虧了我
Shut up! Are you justifying yourself?
開甚麼玩笑？你這個混蛋 你以為你做的事情是對的嗎？
Why did you kill Shinpei's parents?
為甚麼殺了慎平的父母？
Same as Ushio, they got in the way.
因為他們和小潮你一樣，都很礙事啊
They found Hiruko's grotto and tried to make it public.
他們發現了蛭子洞，打算把它公開
They were a foolish couple, but Mother enjoyed her meal.
雖然是一對愚蠢的夫婦 但媽媽也吃得津津有味
Unforgivable.
這傢伙…不可饒恕
I don't want to kill people. You don't want to die, do you?
我不想殺人，你也不想死吧
Why go so far to protect Heine?
為甚麼不惜做到這一步 也要保護波稻？
You're human, so you can't go with Heine to her home.
你是人類 不可能和她一起去她的故鄉
Give up Heine and end this.
交出波稻，這一切不就能結束了嗎？
That is not how I end. My mission is to fulfill Mother's wish.
那不是我的結局 實現媽媽的願望是我的使命
Dammit.
可惡
And you never know. I might have a shadow.
而且說不定我的影子也在
Something is odd.
不對勁
Pull the trigger! I sense no shadows nearby!
快扣下扳機，附近沒有影子的氣息
Why? Why is he...
為甚麼？為甚麼這傢伙…
Shoot, Shinpei! Now is the only chance to kill Shide!
開槍，慎平 要擊倒四手，只有趁現在了
I know what you are thinking.
我知道你現在在想甚麼
Why isn't his left hand burned?
你在想，為甚麼這傢伙的左手 沒有燒傷的痕跡，對吧？
By the way, Shinpei. Can I move?
對了，慎平，我可以動了嗎？
I've had enough. I can't take it anymore!
不行，我忍不了了
Ushioh! Wait!
潮，等等…
He's dead. So that's it?
死了，這樣就結束了嗎？
I said I would do it. I didn't want to make you do this.
不是說了我來嗎？ 我不想讓你做這種事
I can't let you murder someone.
我還是不能讓你殺人
Why not? It was my revenge.
為甚麼？這傢伙是我的仇人啊
You're kind, so you'd have regretted it.
慎平是個好人 殺了人之後肯定會後悔的
You view everyone as people, even me and him.
在你眼裡，我和這樣的傢伙 都是人類吧
Leave all the dirty work to me.
壞事都交給我來做吧
Ushioh.
潮
Let me borrow this.
借我用一下
Did you hear? I killed Shide.
大家都聽到了吧？我殺掉四手了
Shin...
慎…
Okay. One down.
好，搞定一個了
Shide... Why?
四手…為甚麼
No, it can't be. I'm sorry, Shinpei. I didn't notice...
該不會…不可能… 對不起，慎平，我沒發現…
That was so close, Shinpei.
真是可惜啊，慎平
I guess you didn't step back enough to look at the situation.
你的俯瞰還差點火候啊
You're going alone?
你要一個人去？
Persuade him?
要說服他？
I'm against it.
我反對，如果是四手本人 必須毫不猶豫地開槍
I'll kill him.
我去殺了他
No, let me try once.
等一下，請讓我試一次
If I don't know what's on his mind, then I can't kill him.
我想知道那傢伙在想甚麼 否則我下不了手
I want him to tell me himself why he killed my parents.
我想讓他親口告訴我理由 為甚麼殺了我的父母
Otherwise, I'm not satisfied.
否則我完全無法接受
But...
-可是… -為此就算死一次也不算甚麼
I'm still going with you.
我跟你一起去
If the shrine is full of shadows, you won't stand a chance to talk.
如果神社到處埋伏著影子 那你去連說話的機會都沒有
Ushioh is right. If you go alone, they might try to capture you.
潮說得對，如果你一個人去 他們可能會改變計劃，把你抓起來
We'll be on the grounds, too.
我們也去神社院內等你
Fine.
好
Can we somehow hear their conversation?
可以讓我們也聽到談話內容嗎？
Maybe put a phone in your pocket and do multi-way calling?
打開多人通話 然後把手機放在口袋裡怎麼樣
No, you won't be able to hear the conversation clearly.
不行，那樣也聽不清談話內容
We just need to hear gunshots.
那就用槍聲來當暗號吧
I'll shoot twice into his shadow.
先用兩槍打他的影子
If you hear three shots, come in to check if it is human.
確認他是否真的是人類 如果聽到三發槍響，大家就衝進來
Don't you feel like a kid who forgot to save at the end of the game?
你現在是甚麼心情？慎平
Ushioh is dead.
潮死了
Brats.
憑你們幾個小鬼
You thought you could mess with my ending?
就想改變我的結局？
Don't worry. I'm with you, no matter what.
放心吧，無論發生甚麼事 我都會在你身邊
The only loop you will be in is despair and regret.
與你一起進入輪迴的 就只有絕望和後悔了
Take care now.
一路順風
Shinpei really gets led around by the nose.
原來慎平是怕老婆的類型
Yeah! They're like a couple.
嗯，好像夫妻喔，咦…
Huh?
奇怪
Where did Ushioh go?
潮呢？
She was just there.
剛才還在那裡的
Shinpei?
慎平？